good evening
I'm Ruth keiner LEED women voters
education fund
next tuesday is election day before
going to the polls
voters want to understand the issues and
know the candidates positions
tonight voters will have an opportunity
to see in here the major party
candidates
for the presidency state their views
on issues that affect us all the League
of Women Voters
is proud to present this presidential
debate
our moderator it howard K smith
thank you missus Hanover lemme the legal
and boaters is pleased to welcome to the
Cleveland Ohio Convention Center Music
Hall president
jimmy carter the democratic party's
candidate for reelection to the
presidency
and governor Ronald Reagan California
and the Republican Party's candidate for
the presidency
began it will debate %uh questions on
domestic economic foreign policy and
national security issues
be questions are going to be posed by a
panel are distinguished journalists who
you're with me
they are mob in stone the editor at US
News and World Report
Ari Ellis national correspondent to the
Christian Science Monitor
William Hill you did assistant managing
editor through the portland oregonian
barbara walters correspondent ABC News
the ground rules for this is agreed by
you gentleman
by these each panelist down here we'll
ask a question the same question
do each of the two candidates after the
two candidates who ran to the panelist
will ask followup questions would rather
shop in the answers
the candidates will then have an
opportunity each to
to make a rebuttal that will constitute
the first happened the debate in our
state through to the second half later
on
some other rules the candidates are not
permitted to bring prepared notes to the
podium but are permitted to make notes
during the debate
if the candidate sexy the allotted time
agreed on I will
reluctantly but certainly interrupt we
asked the convention center audience
here to abide by one ground-rule please
do not apply on our express approval or
disapproval during the debate
now based on a toss a book on governor
reagan will respond to the first
question from mob in stone
governor as you're well aware
question war and peace has emerged as a
central issue in this campaign and the
give-and-take
recent weeks president carter's been
criticized for responding late too
aggressive soviet impulses
for insufficient build up a firm forces
and a paralysis in dealing with
Afghanistan Iran
you have been criticized for being all
too quick to advocate the use have lots
of muscle
military action to deal with foreign
crises
specifically what are the differences
between the two love you
on the uses american military power I
don't know what the differences might be
because I don't know what mister
carter's policies are
I do know what he said about mine and
I'm only here to tell you that I believe
with all my heart
that our first priority must be
world peace and that use-of-force
is always and only a last resort
when everything else is failed and then
only with regard to our national
security
now I believe
also that this meeting this mission this
responsibility for preserving the peace
which I believe is a responsibility
peculiar to our country
that we cannot shirk our responsibility
as the leader of the free world because
we're the only one that can do it
therefore the burden of maintaining the
peace falls on us
and to maintain that peace requires
strength America has never gotten a war
because we were too strong
we can get into a war by leading events
get out of hand as they have in the last
three and a half years
under the foreign policies of this
administration mister carter's
until we're faced each time with the
crisis
and a good management in preserving the
peace requires that we control
the events and tried to intercept be
four
they become a crisis but
I have seen four wars in my lifetime
I'm a father and sons I have a grandson
I don't ever want to see another
generation of young Americans
lead their lives into sandy beaches in
the pacific or
rice paddies in jungles in the in Asia
or the money but I've
body feels a battlefields of Europe
mister stone do you have a follow-up
question to the governor yes
governor we've been hearing that too the
defense hooker
buildup that you would associate
yourself with would cost tens of
billions of dollars more than is now
contemplated in assuming that the
american people are ready to
bear the scars they never will last keep
asking the following questions:
how do you reconcile huge increases in
military outlays with your promise some
substantial tax cuts
and a balancing the budget which in this
fiscal year
when the just-ended ran more than sixty
billion dollars in the red
mister stone I have submitted an
economic plan
and I worked out in concert with the
number I've fine economist in this
country
all Obama prove it and believe that over
a five-year projection
this plan can permit the extra spending
for
needed refurbishing a bar defensive
posture
that it can provide for a balanced
budget by 1983 if not earlier
and that we can afford along with the
cuts that I a proposed in government
spending
we can afford the tax cuts i proposed
and probably mainly because mister
carter's economic policy has built into
the next five years
and on beyond that a tax increase that
would be taking
$86 billion dollars more next year out
other people's pockets
and was taken this year and my tax cut
does not come close
to eliminating that eighty six billion
dollar increase I'm only reducing the
amount of the increase
in other words what I'm talking about is
not putting government back to getting
less money than governments in getting
but simply cutting the increase the in
in spending
no the same question now goes to
President Carter president I would you
like to have the question repeated
yes so president carter the question War
and Peace a central issue in this
campaign
you been criticized for in the
give-and-take for responding
late too aggressive soviet to impulses
for
insufficient build up a worm forces and
a paralysis in dealing with Afghanistan
and Iran
governor reagan on the other hand has
been criticized for being all too
quick to advocate the use a plot to
muscle military action
to deal with them foreign crises such as
i've mentioned specifically
what are the differences between the two
%uh view on the uses american military
power
bitch down out had to make thousands of
decisions
since I've been president serving in the
oval office
and each one of those decisions that
affect the future my country I have
learned in the process
I think I'm a much wiser more
experienced man and i watch
when I debated for years ago against
president ford
about sewer line that they are no simple
answers to complicated questions
a Jamaican said that for every problem
there's a simple answer
it would be need
and possible and wrong the fact is that
this nation
in eight years before I became president
had its own military
strength decrease
seven out of eight years the budget
commitments for defense went down
thirty-seven percent in all center but
in others we've got a steady
carefully planned methodical but very
effective increase
in our commitment for defense but what
we've done
mystic you that in almost power and
and prestige and military strength love
it United States
to preserve the peace but not only kept
peace for our own country
but we've been able to extend the
benefits apiece to others
in the Middle East we work for peace
treaty between Israel and Egypt
successfully
and have tied ourselves together with
Israel and Egypt
in a common defense capability this
is a very good step forward for our
nation's security
and will continue to do as we've done in
the past
I might also and that they are decisions
that are made in the Oval Office
by every president which upper found in
nature
there are always problems but in the
world and how those
troubled areas are addressed by
president
alone who in that oval office affects
our nation directly
the involvement of the United States and
also our american interest
that is a basic decision has to be made
so frequently
by every president who serves that's
what I try to do successfully by keeping
our country at peace
this is Tanya a follow up on us I i
would like be a little more specific on
the use military power and
let's talk about one area for a moment
under what circumstances would to use
military force is
to deal with for example a shot of a
Persian oiled Gulf
if that should occur are to counter a
russian expansion beyond Afghanistan
into
either Iran or Pakistan I asked this
question and your
charges they we are woefully unprepared
to project sustained and i emphasize the
word sustained
power in that part of the world just
down in my state of the union
address earlier this year a point out
that
any threat to the stability of security
in the persian gulf
would be a threat to the security of our
own country
in the past we've not had an adequate
military presence in that region
now we have two major carry a task
force's
we have access to facilities in five
different areas of that region
and wave made it clear working with our
allies and others
that we are prepared to address any
foreseeable eventuality
which by in a rut commerce with a
crucial area the world
but in doing this we have made sure that
we address this question
peacefully not injecting American
military forces in the combat
but letting a straight about nation be
felt in a beneficial way
this I believe has should that I ages
will be protected in the
Persian Gulf region as we've done in the
Middle East
and throughout the world governor reagan
you have a minute to comment or rebut
but yes I question the figure about the
decline in
a defense spending under the two
previous administrations and
appreciating eight years to this
administration
I would call your attention that too we
were in a warrant that wound down during
those eight years which of course made a
change in
military spending because I've returning
from war to peace
I also would like to point out the
republican presidents in those years
faced with the Democratic majority in
both houses of the congress
found that their request for defense
budgets were very often cut
now Gerald Ford left
a 5-year projected plan for a military
build-up to restore our defenses in
president carter's administration
reduced at by 38 percent cut sixty ships
out within a building program that have
been proposed
and stop the
the B-one delayed the cruise missile
stop the production line for the
Minuteman missile stop it right answer
delay the tridents
submarine and now is planning a mobile
military force that can be delivered to
various spots in the world
which does make me question his assaults
on whether I am the one that ish
quick to look for use a force president
carter you have the last word on this
question
whatever's elements up when someone is
to control nuclear weapons which I hope
will get to you later on because that's
a modest
important single issue in this campaign
another one is how to address trouble
areas in the world I think habitually
governor reagan is advocated the
injection a military forces into trouble
areas
when I and my predecessors both
Democrats and Republicans
have advocated resolving those troubled
and those difficult difficult areas in
the world
peacefully diplomatically and through
negotiation
in addition to that the buildup of
military forces
is good for our country because we've
got to have military strength in order
to preserve the peace
but I'll always remember that the best
weapons
other one to the other part in combat
and the best soldier is one who never
has to laid his life down
on the field of battle spring
is imperative for p but the two must go
hand in hand
thank you gentleman the next question is
from Harry Ellis to president carter
mister president when you are elected in
the consumer price index stood at 4.8
percent
it now stands at more than 12 percent
perhaps more significantly the nation's
broader
underlying inflation rate has gone up
from seven to nine percent
now a part of that was due to external
factors beyond US control notably
the more than doubling about oil prices
by OPEC last year
because the United States remains
vulnerable to such external shocks can
inflation in fact
be controlled if so what measures would
you pursue
in a second term
again it's important to put Leone
situation into perspective
in 1974 we had a so-called oil shock
where an the price of opec always raised
it to an extraordinary degree
we had an even worse all shock in 1979
in 1974 we had the worst recession
the deepest and most penetrating
recession since the Second World War
the recession that resulted this time
was a British we've had since the second
world war
in addition we brought down inflation
earlier this year the first quarter we
did have a very severe
inflation pressure brought about by the
opec price increase do everything about
18 percent the first quarter this year
the second quarter
we had dropped it down to about 13
percent the most recent figures the last
three months to the third quarter this
year
inflation rate is seven percent still to
mine
but it illustrates very vividly that in
addition to providing
anonymous number of jobs nine million
new jobs in the last three and a half
years
that inflationary threat is still urgent
ownership
I noticed the governor reagan reason I
mention that reagan camp roth proposal
which is already made george bush this
crime as Buddha economics
and said it would result in a 30 percent
inflation right
and BusinessWeek which is not a
democratic publication said
that this reagan can run proposal and I
quote them I think
was completely irresponsible and would
result
inflationary pressures which would
destroy this nation
so %ah proposals are very sound and very
carefully considered
to stimulate jobs to improve them
the industrial complex in this country
to create tools for american workers
then at the same time would be
anti-inflationary and nature
so dad nine million new jobs to control
inflation and to plan for the future was
a
energy policy now and tagged as a
foundation
is our plan for the years ahead mister
others do you have a follow-up question
for mister carter
yes mister president you have mentioned
the creation of 9 million new jobs
at the same time the unemployment rate
still hangs high
as does the inflation rate now I wonder
can you tell us what additional policies
you would pursue
in a second administration in order to
try to bring down
that inflation rate and would it be an
active leadership
to tell the american people they're
going to have to sacrifice
to adopt a leaner lifestyle for some
time to come
yes we have demanded that the American
people sacrifice and they've done very
well
as a matter of fact we are importing
today
about one-third less all from overseas
than we did just a year ago
we've had a 25 percent reduction to
firstly I was in office
at the same time as I said earlier we
have added about nine million net new
jobs in that period of time
a record number will for cheap also the
new energy policy has been predicated on
two factors one
conservation which require sacrificed
and the other one increase in production
American energy which is going along
very well more call the sheer
than ever before in history mall and gas
wells drilled this year
than ever before in history the new
economic
revitalization program we have in mind
which will be implemented next year
would result in tax credits
which would let businesses invest in new
to a new fact is to create even more new
jobs about a million
in the next two years and we also have
planned a youth
employment program which would encompass
600,000 jobs for young people
this is already passed the House now has
a national prospect passed Senate
now the same question goes to governor
reagan governor reagan would you like to
have the question repeated
governor again during the past four
years the consumer price index
has risen from 4.8 percent to currently
over twelve percent and perhaps more
significantly the nation's broader
underlying rate of inflation is gone up
from seven to nine percent
now a partner that has been due to
external factors beyond US control
and notably the more than doubling up a
pack of oil prices last year
which leads me to ask you whether since
the United States
remains vulnerable to such external
shocks
can inflation in fact be controlled
if so specifically what measures would
you pursue
mister ellis I think this idea that has
been
respond here in our country that
inflation somehow came up on it's like a
plague and therefore it's uncontrollable
and no one can do anything about it
is entirely spurious and its dangerous
to say this to the people
I'm just gonna became president
inflation was 4.8 percent as you said it
had been cut into
by President Gerald Ford it is now
running a 20.7 percent
president carter also has spoken at the
new jobs created what we always with the
normal growth in our country an increase
in population
increase the number of jobs but that
can't hide the fact that there are eight
million
men and women out of work in america
today and two million to those lost
their jobs in just the last few months
to Goddard also promised that he would
not use unemployment as a tool to fight
against inflation
and yet his 1980 economic message stated
that we would reduce productivity and
gross national product and increase
unemployment
in order to get a handle on inflation
because a in January at the beginning of
the year it was more than 18 percent
since then he has blamed to the people
for inflation opec
he blamed the Federal Reserve System he
has blamed the lack of productivity the
American people
he is then accused the people who live
in too well and
that we must share in scarcity we must
sacrifice and get used to doing with
less
we don't have inflation because the
people living too well we have inflation
because the government
is living too well and the last
statement
just a few days ago was a speech to the
effect that
we have inflation because government
revenues have not kept pace with
government spending
I see my time is running out here I have
to get this down very fast
yes you can lick inflation by increasing
productivity
and by decreasing the cost the
government to the place that we have
balanced budgets
and i no longer running grinding are
printing press money
flooding the market with it because the
government is spending more than it
takes in and my economic plan calls for
that
the president's economic plan calls for
increasing
but taxes to the point that we finally
takes so much money away from the people
but we can balance the budget in that
way but we'll have a very poor nation
and a very unsound economy if we follow
that path a follow-up
mister allen's yes you have centered on
cutting government spending in what you
have just said about
your own policies you have also said
that you would it increased defense
spending
specifically where would you cut
government spending
if you were to increase defense spending
and
also cut taxes so that presumably
federal revenues would shrink well
most people when they think about
cutting government spending they think
in terms of eliminating
necessary programs or wiping out
something some service the government is
supposed to perform
I believe that there is another
extravagance in fact in government
as a matter a fact term one of the
secretaries have a GW under mister
carter testified that he thought there
was seven billion dollars worth of fraud
the and waste in welfare and in the
medical programs associated with it
we've had the general accounting office
estimated
there is probably tens of billions of
dollars that is lost in fraud alone and
they have added that
waist adds even more to that we have a
program for a gradual reduction of
government spending
based on these theories and I have a
task force now that I've been working on
where those cuts could be made I'm
confident that it can be done
and that it will reduce inflation
because I did
in California and inflation went down
below the national average in California
when we return money to the people and
reduced government spending
president carter Ham
governor reagan's proposal the red ink
Mr of proposal
is one of the most highly inflationary
ideas that have a has been presented to
the american public
he would actually have to cut government
spending
Palace 230 billion dollars in order to
balance a budget under this ridiculous
proposal
I notice that this task force is working
for his future plans
had some other ideas revealed in the
wall street journal this week
one of those ideas was to repeal the
minimum wage
and several times this year governor
reagan has said
that the major cause unemployment is the
minimum wage
this is a heart this kind of approach to
the working families about country which
is typical
but many republican leaders in the past
but I think has been accentuated under
governor reagan in California
I'm surprised given reagan brought this
up
he had three largest tax increases
in history that state under his
administration
he more than doubled state spending
while he was governor 120 percent
increase
and have between 20 and 30 percent
increase in the number of employees
Sara din and California route thank you
sir it's a governor reagan has the last
word on this budget
yes the figures that the president is
just used about California
and is a distortion of the situation
there
because while I was governor of
California
are spending in California increased
less per capita
than the spending in Georgia almost
Carter was governor
Georgia in the same four years the size
of government
increased only 16 in California
I've wanted increased in proportion to
population in Georgia
and the idea that my tax cut proposal is
inflationary I would like to ask the
president
why is it inflationary to let the people
keep more of their money and spend it
the way they'd like
and it isn't inflationary to let him
take that money and spend it the way he
wants
I wish that question need not be
rhetorical but it must be because we run
out of time on that
Maltby the third third question
to governor reagan from William Hill you
yes governor reagan the decline in
garcetti's has been hastened by the
continual rise in crime
strain race relations befallen the
quality of public education
the persistent a bad number poverty in a
rich nation
may decline in the services to the
public the signs seem to point what I D
Terry Asian
that could lead to the establishment at
the promenade underclass
in the city's what specifically would
you do in the next four years
to reverse this trend I have been
talking to a number of congressman
who have much the same idea that I hear
and that is that in the inner city areas
that in cooperation with local
government
and with national government and using
tax incentives and Whincup cooperation
with the private sector
but we have development zones what the
local
entity the city declare this particular
area based on the standards have
the percentage of people on welfare
unemployed and so forth in that area
and then through tax incentives induced
the creation a business is providing
jobs and so forth in those areas
the elements have government through
these tax incentives for example a
business that would not have for a
period of time
an increase in the property tax
reflecting its development of the unused
property
that it was making wouldn't be any loss
to the city
because she isn't getting any tax from
that now and would simply be a delay
and on the other hand many of the people
that would then be given jobs are
presently words have the government
and wouldn't hurt to give them a tax
incentive because im
they that wouldn't be costing government
anything either
I think there are things to do in this
regard I stood in the south bronx
on the exact spot the president aristede
on in 1977
you have to see it to believe it it
looks like a bombed-out city
great gone skeletons a building's
windows smashed out
painted on one of them unkept promises
on another despair
and miss with this bad which President
Carter had promised
that he was going to bring in bass
program to rebuild this department
their home or this area their whole
blocks of land that are left bare
I'll just bulldoze down flat
and nothing has been done and they are
now charging to take tourists through
there to see
this terrible desolation I talk to a man
just briefly there who asked me one
simple question
do I have reason to hope that I can
someday take care of my family again
nothing has been done follow-up mister
him
yes governor reagan blacks and other
non-whites are increasing in numbers in
our cities
many of them feel that they are facing a
hostility from right
that prevents them from joining the
economic mainstream a bar society
there's racial confrontation in the
schools on jobs
and housing is non-white seek to reap
the benefit to the free society
what do you think is the nation's future
as a multi-racial society
I believe in it I am eternally
optimistic and I happen to believe that
we've made great progress from
the days when I was young and when this
country didn't even know what had a
racial problem
I know those things can grow out of
despair in an inner-city
and when there's hopelessness that at
home
lack of work and so forth but I believe
that all of us together and I believe
the presidency is what teddy roosevelt
said it was it a bully pulpit
and I think that something can be done
from there because the goal for all of
us should be
that one day things will be done neither
because I'm
nor in spite of any of the differences
between us
ethnic differences are racial distrust
differences whatever they may be
but we will have total equal opportunity
for all people and I would do everything
I could in my power
to bring that about mister Hilliard
would you repeat your question for
president carter im
president carter the decline have our
cities has been hastened by the
continual rise in crime
strain race relations befallen the
quality of public education
the persistence of have normal poverty
in a rich nation
and a decline in services to the public
the signs seem to point to a
deterioration
that could lead to the establishment of
the permit underclass in the city's
what specifically would you do in the
next four years to reverse this trend
equity but I was campaigning in 1976
very well when the mayors and local
officials were in despair
about the rapidly deteriorating central
cities have a nation
we initiated a very fine urban renewal
program
working with the mayor's the governors
and other interested officials
this is Ben a very successful effort
that's one of the main reasons that
we've had such an increase in the number
of people employed
other nine million people put to work a
new job since I've been in office
1.3 million of those has been among
black Americans
another million among those who speak
Spanish
we now planning to to continue
the revitalization program with
increased
commitments of rapid transit mass
transit
under the windfall profits tax we expect
to spend about forty
three billion dollars and the next 10
years
to rebuild a transportation system to
backcountry we also are pursuing
housing programs we've had a 73 percent
increase
and allotment of federal funds for
improved education
these are the kinds of efforts worked on
a joint bases with community leaders
particular in a minority areas other
central cities that had been
deteriorating so rapidly in the past
it's very important to us that this be
done with a full involvement
minority citizens I brought into the
top-level top-level to government
into the white house into administrative
offices about the executive branch
inode into the judicial system highly
qualified
black and Spanish citizens and women who
in the past had been excluded
I notice a governor reagan said it when
he was a a young man
that there was no knowledge of a racial
problem in this country
those who suffered from discrimination
because a brace
or sect certain in New we had a racial
problem
we have gone a long way to a correcting
these problems
but we still have a long way to go
follow-up question
best present I don't like to see repeat
the same follow up to you
blacks in other non-white to increasing
in numbers in our cities
minute didn't feel that they are facing
hostility from whites that prevents them
from joining the economic mainstream a
bar society
there's racial computation the school's
on jobs and housing is non-white seek to
reap the benefit to the free society
what is your assessment at the nation's
as a featured in a multi-racial society
ours is a nation are full refugees
a nation of immigrants almost all our
citizens came here from
other lands and now have hopes
which are being realized forgot a life
preserving their ethnic commitments
their family structures their religious
beliefs
preserving their relationships with
their relatives in foreign countries
but still following themselves together
in a very coherent society
which gives our nation in strength in
the past
those minority groups have often been
excluded from participation in the
affairs of government
since i've been president have appointed
president
more than twice as many black federal
judges
as all previous presidents in history
this country
I done the same thing and Department of
women and also
spanish-speaking Americans to involve
them in administration of government
and a feeling that they belong to the
societal structure that makes decisions
in the judiciary and executive branch is
a very
important commitment which I am trying
to realize I will continue to do so
in the future governor reagan you have a
minute rebuttal yes
the president talks Obama programs and
they have their place but as governor
when I was at that
into the line and receiving some of
these grants for government programs I
saw that so many of them were dead and
they were public employment for these
people who really want to get out into
the
private job market where there are jobs
with the future
and the president spoke a moment ago
about but I was against the minimum wage
I wish she could have been with me when
i sat with a group of
teenagers who were black and who were
telling me about their unemployment
problems
and that it was the minimum wage that
had done away with the jobs that they
once could get
and indeed every time it is increased
you will find that there is an increase
in minority
unemployment among young people and
therefore I have been in favor
%uh a separate minimum for them
with regard to the great progress that
has been made with this government
spending
the raid a black unemployment in Detroit
Michigan is fifty six percent
president carter you have the last word
on this question
well it's obvious that we still have a
long way to go and fully incorporating
the minority groups into the mainstream
of American life
we have made good progress and is no
doubt in my mind that the commitment to
unemployment compensation a minimum wage
welfare national health insurance those
kind of commitment
that have to provide the Democratic
Party since
ancient history in this country's
political life are very important
element of the future
in all those elements governor reagan
has repeatedly spoken out against them
which to me showed a very great
insensitivity to giving
deprived families a better chance in
life
this to me is a very important
difference between him
and me in this election and i believe
the american people will judge
accordingly
there's no doubt in my mind that in the
downtown central cities
with the with the new commitment on an
energy policy
with a chance to revitalize home to make
them more
fuel-efficient where the chance for
synthetic synthetic fuels program
solar power this will give us an
additional I'll tunity for jobs which
will pay rich dividends back you
gentleman
now for the fourth question to president
carter from barbara walters
the president the EISA the country
tonight on the hostages in Iran
I realize this is a sensitive area but
the question of how we respond to acts
of terrorism
goes beyond this current crisis other
countries have policies that determine
how they will respond
Israel for example considers hostages
like soldiers and will not negotiate
with terrorists
for the future mister president the
country has the right to know do you
have a policy for dealing with terrorism
wherever it might happen and what did we
learn from this experience
in around that might cause us to do
things differently
if this was something similar happens
again
brother wanted the blige on this
world is a threat and the activities of
terrorists
one other reason economic summit
conferences between myself
and the other leaders are the Western
world we committed ourselves to take
strong action against terrorism
airplane hijacking was one elements %uh
that commitment
there's no doubt that we have
seen in recent years in recent months
additional tax a balanced against Jews
and
France and of course against those who
live in Israel by the PO and other
terrorist organizations
ultimately the most serious terrorist
threat
is if one of those radical nation to
believe in terrorism in a policy
should have atomic weapons
both I and all my predecessors had a
deep commitment to controlling the
proliferation
have nuclear weapons in countries like
Libya all iraq
we have even alienated some about poses
trade partners because we have insisted
upon the control
up the spread of nuclear weapons to
those potentially terrorist countries
when governor reagan has been asked
about then he makes a very disturbing
comment
that nonproliferation other control the
spread of nuclear weapons
is not about business and when he was
asked specifically racially about iraq
he said there's nothing we can do about
it this ultimate
terrorist threat is the most fearsome a
ball
and as part of a pattern where our
country must stand firm
to control terrorism of all kinds
miss waters a follow-up yes
while we are discussing policy head
around not taken American hostages I
assume that in order to preserve our
neutrality
we would have stopped the flowers spare
parts and vital raw materials want war
broke out between
Iraq and Iran now offering to lift the
ban on such goods if there are people
come home
doesn't this me more I'm terrorism
compromise our neutrality
and possibly antagonized nations now
family to rise in the Middle East
we will maintain no position and
neutrality
in the iran and the right wall we have
no plans to sell
additional material all goods to Iran
that might be able like nature when I'm
made my decision to stop all trade with
Iran
as a result other taking about hostages
I announced they're not have
consistently maintained since then
that if the hostages are released safely
that we would make delivery on those
items
which Iran owns which I have bought and
paid for
also that the frozen Iranian assets
would be released that's been a
consistent policy
19 10 Dec area but you repeat the
question now for governor again please
meet want me
yes governor the either the country
tonight remain on the hostages in Iran
with the question of how we respond to
acts of terrorism goes beyond this
current crisis
there are other countries that have
policies that determine how they will
respond
Israel for example considers hostages
like soldiers and will not negotiate
with terrorists
for the future country has the right to
know do you have a policy
dealing with terrorism wherever it might
happen
and what we learned from this experience
in Iraq and that might cause us to do
things differently if this was something
similar
should happen again bar you there's that
question twice I think you want to have
at least one answer to it
I am I have been accused of
lately I'm having a secret plan with
regard to the hostages
now this comes from an answer that I had
made at least 50 times during this
campaign to the press
which is the the question would be: have
you any ideas of what you would do if
you were there
and I said well yes and I think that
anyone seeking this position
as well as other people probably have
thought to themselves
what about this what about that these
are just ideas
what I would think I've if I were in
that position and had access to the
information in which I would know all
the options that were open to me
I have never answered the question
however second
the one the same as well tell me what
are some %uh those ideas first of all I
would be fearful that I might say
something that was
presently underway are in negotiations
and does expose it and
endanger the hostages and sometimes I
think some of my ideas might involve
quiet diplomacy where you don't say in
advance or say to anyone
what it is you're thinking doing your
question is difficult to answer
because in the situation right now
no one wants to say anything that would
inadvertently
delay in any way the return of those
hostages at their
if there is a chance for the coming home
soon or that might cause them harm
but I do think should be done once they
are safely here
with their families in that tragedy is
over and we've been doing this
humiliation for just lacking one week of
the year now
then I think it is time for us to have a
complete investigation
as to the diplomatic efforts that were
made in the beginning
why a they have been there so long and
when they come home what did we have to
do in order to bring that about
what arrangements were made and I would
suggest that congress
should hold such an investigation in the
meantime I'm going to continue praying
that they'll come home
follow-up question I would like to say
that neither candidate answer
specifically the question no
I have a specific policy for dealing
with terrorism but I will ask governor
reagan &
different following question: you've had
suggested that there would be no Iranian
prices had you been president
because we would have given family
support to the shock
but Iran is a country of 237 million
people who are resisting a government
today regarded as dictatorial
my question is not whether the show was
busy regime was preferable to the
ayatollahs
but whether the United States has the
power or the right to try to determine
what form a government any country will
have
and do we back unpopular regimes whose
major merit isn't that they are friendly
to the United States
the degree oven popularity over regime
when the choice is total
authoritarianism
I totalitarianism I should say
in the alternative government makes one
wonder whether you
are being helpful to the people and
we've been guilty of that
because someone didn't meet exactly our
standards have human rights even though
they were an ally a barge
instead of trying patiently to persuade
them to change their ways
we have in a number of instances
aidid a revolutionary overthrow which
results in complete totalitarianism
instead for those people and I think
that this is a Condo hypocritical policy
when the same time we're maintaining a
detente with the one nation in the world
where there are no human rights at all
the Soviet Union now there was a second
phase
in the around in a fair in which we had
something to do with that
and that was we had adequate warning
that there was a threat to our embassy
and we could have done what other
embassies do neither strengthen our
security there
or remove our personnel before
the kidnapping the takeover took place
the other I'm sorry I missed interrupt
president carter you have a minute for
rebuttal
I didn't hear any come in from governor
reagan about what he would do to stop
for the reduced terrorism in the future
but the western allies did decide to do
is to stop all air flights commercial
airplanes to any nation and bald
in terrorism hijacking a plane to the
harboring up hijackers
secondly we all committed ourselves as I
love my predecessors in the oval office
not to permit the spread of nuclear
weapons
to a terrorist nation or to any other
nation that does not presently have
those weapons or capabilities for
explosives
third not to make any sale to material
weapons
to an Asian which is involved in
terrorist activities
and last but not to deal with a pillow
until and unless the P lol recognizes
Israel's right to exist
and recognizes UN resolution 242 as a
basis for Middle East peace
these are a few other things to which
our nation is committed
and we will continue with these
commitments been governor reagan you
have the last word on that question
yes I have no quarrel whatsoever with
the things that have been done because I
believe it is high time
that the civilized countries in the
world made it plain that there is no
room worldwide
for terrorism there will be no
negotiation with
terrorist have any kind and while I have
a last word here I would like to correct
a misstatement of fact by the
president's
I I have never made the statement that
he suggested about
nuclear proliferation and nuclear
proliferation or the trying to
hold it would be an major part of the
foreign policy of mine
thank you gentleman bad as the first
half for the debate now the rules for
the second half
quite simple there only complicated when
I explain them
the him second half the panel is with me
will have no followup questions
instead after the panelists have asked a
question
the candidates have answered each of the
candidates will have two opportunities
to follow up
to question to rebut are just a comment
on his opponent statement
governor reagan will respond in this
section to the first question for mob in
stone
governor reagan arms control president
said it was the single most important
issue
both love you will have expressed the
desire than the nuclear arms way
race with russia but by methods that are
vastly different
you suggest that we scrap the salt two
treaty already negotiated
and intensify the build-up American
power
in to induce the soviets to sign a new
treaty
one more favorable to us yes president
carter on the other hand
says he will again trying to convince a
reluctant Congress
to ratify the present treaty and the
ground it's the best we can hope to get
both you cannot be right will you tell
us why you think you are
yes I think I'm right because I believe
that we must have a consistent foreign
policy a strong america and a strong
economy
and then as we build up on national
security
to restore our margin of safety we have
the same time try to restrain
the soviet build-up which has been going
forward
a rapid pace and for quite some time
the shot two treaty was the result of
negotiations
mister carter's team entered into after
he had asked
the Soviet Union for a discussion on
actual reduction
have nuclear strategic weapons and his
emissary
I think a moment twelve hours with
having heard
a very definite net but taking that one
no
from the Soviet Union we then went back
into negotiations on their terms because
mister carter had canceled the B-one
bomber
delay the MX delay the Trident submarine
delayed the cruise missile shut down the
missile man
but three the Minuteman a missile
production line
and whatever other things that that
might have been done the Soviet Union
sat at the table knowing that we had
gone for with unilateral
considerate up concessions without any
reciprocation from them whatsoever
now I have not blocked the salt two
treaty as
card and mister mondale suggest that I
have it has been blocked by a Senate in
which there is a democratic majority
indeed the Senate Armed Services
Committee voted 10 to 0 with seven
abstentions
against the salt two treaty and declared
that it was not
in these national security interest on
the United States
besides which it is illegal because the
law of the land passed by Congress says
we cannot
except the treaty in which we are not
equal
and we're not equal in this treaty for
one reason alone
are B-fifty two bombers are considered
to be strategic weapons
their backfire bombers are not the
governor at dinner up to that point
time's up for that but the same question
now to president carter
yes sir president carter both the viewer
expressed the desire them the nuclear
arms wave
race with russia but through vastly
different methods
the governor suggest we scrap the salt
two treaty
which you negotiated Indiana I R sign to
me and intensify the build-up American
power to induce the soviets to sign a
new treaty
10 more favorable to us you on the other
hand
say you will again try to convince a
reluctant Congress to ratify the present
treaty
on the grounds it is the best we can
hope to get from the russians
you cannot both be right will you tell
us why you think a
you are yes I'll be granted
the inflation unemployment thus it is
all very important issues but they pale
into insignificance
in their life and it is a president when
compared with the control of nuclear
weapons
every president who has served in the
Oval Office Center truman
has been dedicated to the proposition of
controlling nuclear weapons
to negotiate with the Soviet Union
balanced
controlled observable and then
reducing levels atomic weaponry
there is a disturbing pattern an
attitude governor reagan
he has never supported any of those arms
control agreements
the limited test ban salt 1
know that the the anti-ballistic missile
treaty
not a bottom-up stock traded negotiated
with the Soviet Union by
president ford and now he wants to throw
into the wastebasket
a treaty to control nuclear weapons on a
balanced an equal basis
between ourselves and the soviet union
negotiated over a seven-year period
by myself and my to republican
predecessors
the senate has not voted yet on the
strategic arms limitation treaty
there have been preliminary skirmishing
in the committed to the senate
but the treaty has never come to the
floor of the senate for you to a debate
or a bowl it's understandable that a
senator
in the preliminary debate can make an
irresponsible statement
a maybe an ill-advised statement you've
got 99 other senators to correct
that mistake if it is a mistake but one
a man who hopes to be president says
take this treaty
discarded do not vote do not debate
do not explore the issues do not
finally capitalize on this long
negotiation
that is a very dangerous and disturbing
thing governor reagan you have an
opportunity to rebut that
yes I'd like to respond very much first
of all
the Soviet Union if I have been critical
of some other previous agreements is
because we've been
out negotiated for all quite a long time
and they have managed in spite of all
OVR
attempts and arms limitation took to go
forward with the biggest military
buildup in the history of man
now to suggest that because two
republican presidents tried to
pass the salt Rudy treaty that puts them
on its side I would like to say
but president ford who is within ninety
percent
up in a tree a treaty that we could be
in agreement with when he left office
is emphatically against this salt treaty
I would like to point out also that
senators like an rejection and
hollinger South Carolina they are taking
the lead in the fight
against this particular treaty I am NOT
talking to scrapping
I am talking up taking the treaty back
and going back into negotiations and I
would say to the soviet union we will
sit and negotiate with you as long as it
takes
to have not only legitimate arms
limitation
but to have a reduction of these nuclear
weapons to the point that neither one of
us represents a threat to the other
that is hardly throwing away a treaty
and being opposed to arms limitation
present current yes
a regular rate is making some very
misleading and disturbing statements
he not only advocates the scrapping of
this treaty and I don't know that these
men and he quotes
are against a tree in his final poll but
he also advocates a possibility
he said it's been a missing element
applying a trump card
against the Soviet Union other nuclear
arms race
and insisting upon nuclear superiority
by our own nation as a predication for
negotiation in the future with the
Soviet Union
if president brezhnev said we will scrap
this treaty
negotiated under three american
presidents over seven year period of
time
we insist upon nuclear superiority as a
basis for future negotiations
and we believe that the launching up a
nuclear arms race
is a good basis for future negotiations
it's obvious that I as president an
all-american would reject such a
proposition
this would mean the resumption a very
dangerous
nuclear arms race it would be a very
disturbing to American people
it would change the basic tone and
commitment that our nation has
experienced
ever since the second world war with all
presidents democratic and republican
and would also be very disturbing to
allies all of whom
support this nuclear arms treaty in
addition to that
the adversarial relationship between
ourselves and the Soviet Union
what on down to deteriorate very rapidly
this attitude
is extremely dangers in the lead role in
this tome
although it said with the choirboys
governor reagan
know the president's supposed to be
replying to me but sometimes I have a
hard to have been connecting what he's
saying
with what I have said what my position
Zack
sometimes think like the witch doctor
the gets mad when a good doctor comes
along with a cute little work
me my
point I have made already ex-president
with regard to
negotiating it does not call for nuclear
superiority in the party the United
States
it is calls for a mutual reduction on
these weapons
as I say to the point that neither of us
can represent a threat
to the other and to suggest that the
salt two treaty that your negotiators
negotiated
was just a continuation and based on all
of the
appreciating average by two previous
presidents is just not true
it was a new negotiation because as i
say president ford
was within about 10 percent having a
solution that could be acceptable and I
think our allies
would be very happy to go along with the
fair
and verifiable shot agreement
president carter you have the last word
on this question
I think to close at this discussion it
would be better to put into perspective
but we're talking about I had a
discussion with my daughter Amy
the other day before I came here to ask
what the most important issue what she
said she thought nuclear weaponry
the and the control of nuclear arms
this his upper middle portion
some of these weapons have 10 megatons
explosion
if you put fifty times AT&T in each
10 railroad cars you would have a
carlotta TNT
a train or TNT stretching across this
nation that's one
major war explosion
in a warhead we have
thousand equivalent
up megaton all million tons of TNT
warhead
the control of these weapons is the
single major responsibility for
president
and the cash down this commitment of all
presidents
because of some slight technicalities
that can be corrected
is a very dangerous to approach we have
to go to another question now
from Harry Ellis to president carter
mister president as you have said
Americans through conservation are
importing much less oil today than we
were even a year ago
yet US dependence on Arab oil
as a percentage of total imports is
today much higher than it was
at the time of the 1973 Arab Oil Embargo
and for some time to come the law so
substantial amounts in Arab oil
could plunge the US into depression
now this means that a bridge must be
built out at this dependence
can the united states develop
synthetic fuels and other alternative
energy sources
without damage to the environment and
will this process mean steadily higher
fuel bills for american families
I don't think is in town then the future
the cost of oil is going to go up
what I've had as a basic commitment to
tab and as president
is to reduce our dependence on foreign
oil they can only be done in two ways
want to conserve energy to stop the
wasted energy
and secondly to produce more American
energy we've been very successful in
both cases
we've now reduced importing a foreign
all in the last year old
by one-third we imported today
2 million barrels a ball less damn good
at the same day
just a year ago this commitment has been
opening up a very bright investor for a
nation in the future
because with the when Paul profits tax
as a base
we now have an opportunity to use
american technology
an American ability in america natural
resources
to expand rapidly the production of
synthetic fuels yes
solar energy yes
and also to produce a conventional kind
of American energy
we will grill all and gas wells this
year than any
year in history will produce more polish
eum
than any year in history we are
exporting more coal this year
than any year in history and we have an
opportunity now
with improved transportation systems
improve loading facilities in our port
to see a very good opportunity on it
world international market
to replace OPEC oil with American coal
as a basic images source: this exciting
future
were not only give us more energy
security will also open up vast
opportunities for americans to live a
better life and I have millions of new
jobs associated with
this new and very dynamic industry now
in prospect because %uh the new energy
policy we put into effect
would you repeat the question now the
governor reagan
governor reagan Americans through
conservation are importing much less oil
today then
we were even a year ago and yet US
reliance on Arab oil as a
percentage of total imports is much
higher today than it was during the 1973
Arab Oil Embargo
and the substantial loss of Arab oil
could plunge the united states and a
depression
the question is whether the development
%uh alternative energy sources
in order to reduce this dependence can
be done
without damaging the environment and
will it mean for american families
steadily higher fuel bills
I'm not so sure the remains deadly
higher fuel cost
but I do believe that this nation has
been portrayed for too long a time to
the people as being energy poor
when it is energy-rich the call the
president mentioned yes we have it in
yet 18 the bar
total coal resources is not being
utilized at all
right now the mines are closed down
there a twenty-two thousand miners out
of work
most to this is due to regulations which
either interfere with the mining have a
or prevent the burning up in with our
modern technology
yes we can Bernard call within the
limits of the Clean Air Act
I think as technology improves will be
able to do even better with that
the other thing years that we have only
least out
begun to explore 2 percent of our outer
continental shelf
for oil where it is believed by everyone
from any with that
if you will and that source of energy
but there are vast supply ship to be
found
our government has in the last year's
show taken I would've
multiple use millions have acreage
of public lands that once were
while the Republic land subject to
multiple use exploration for minerals
and so forth it is believed that
probably
seventy percent and the potential oil in
the United States
is probably hidden in those lands
and no one is allowed to even go and
explore to find out if it is there this
is particularly true of the region
average to shut down part of alaska
nuclear power there were 36 power plants
planned in this country and let me add
the word safety it must be done with the
utmost to safety
but 32 of those had given up and cancel
their plans to build
and again because government regulations
and permits and so forth take
make it take more than twice as long to
build a nuclear plant in the United
States as it does to build one in Japan
or in Western Europe
we have the sources here we are
energy-rich
and call is one of the great potentials
we had
president Garry O'Connor mission
therapy myself we have
this year the opportunity
which will realize to produce $800
million tons of coal
and on equaled record in the history of
our country
governor reagan says that this is not a
good achievement
any blames restraints on coal production
on regulations
regulations that affect the light and
the health and safety of miners
and also regulation to protect the
purity of our area
and a quality about water and on land we
cannot cast aside those regulations
we have a chance in the next 15 years
insisting upon the
help and safety up workers
in the mines and also preserving the
same high
air and water pollution standards to
triple the amount of coal we produce
governor reagan's approach to our energy
policy
which is already proven its
effectiveness is to repeal of to change
substantial the windfall profits tax
to return a major portion of $227
billion dollars back to all companies
to do away with the Department of Energy
to short-circuit
are synthetic fuels program to put a
minimum
%um emphasis on solar power to emphasize
strongly
nuclear power plant as a major source of
energy in the future
you want to put all our eggs in one
basket and give that basket
to the major oil companies governor
reagan
that is a misstatement of course have my
position I just happen to believe that
free enterprise can do a better job
producing the things that people need
then government can the Department of
Energy has a multi-billion dollar budget
in excess of $10 billion dollars it has
introduced a portable Winter Olympic
collar anything else no wind energy
and for the win mister carter to suggest
the I want to do away with the safety
laws
and with the laws that pertain to clean
water and clean air and so forth
as governor of California I don't charge
a passing the strictest
air pollution laws in the United States
the strictest air quality law that has
ever been adopted in the United States
and we created an ocean
an occupational safety and health agency
for the protection of employees
before the federal government had one in
place and to this day
not one of its decisions are rulings has
ever been challenged
so I think some those charges are
missing the point
I am suggesting that there are literally
thousands of
unnecessary regulations
but invade every facet a business and
indeed very much about personal lives
that are unnecessary the government can
do without that added a 130 billion
dollars to the cost of production in
this country
and that are contributing their part
add to inflation and I would like to say
yes
a little more free as we once were
president carter another crack at that
sure as a matter fact the air pollution
standard laws that were passed in
california passed over
the objections of governor reagan and
this is a very well known fact
also racially when someone suggested
that the Occupational Safety and Health
Act should be abolished
governor reagan responded a man
they offshore drilling rights
is a question that governor reagan
raises often as a matter fact
in the proposal for the alaska lands
legislation
a hundred percent of all the offshore
land would be open for exploration
ninety-five percent of all the alaska
lands were it is suspected
I believe that mineral members might
exist
we have with our five year plan for the
leasing a lot sure land
proposed moral land to be drilled
than has been open up for drilling sense
this program for started in 1954
so we're not putting restraint on
American exploration we're encouraging
it in every way we can.
governor reagan you have the last word
on this question yes
if it is a well-known fact that I
opposed air pollution laws in California
the only thing I can possibly think I
visit the president must be suggesting
the law that the federal government
tried to impose on the state of
California nadolol
regulations that would have made it
impossible to drive an automobile within
the city limits have any California city
or have a place to put it if you did
driver against their regulations
it would have destroyed the economy of
california and I must say we had the
support of congress when we pointed out
how ridiculous this attempt was by the
Environmental Protection Agency
we still have the strictest air
controller air pollution laws
in the country as for offshore oil in
only 2 percent now
is so least and is producing oil
at the the rest as to whether the open
their lands are going to be opened
in the next five years or so we're
already five years behind
in what we should be doing there is more
oil now in the wells that have been
drilled
then has been taken out in a hundred and
twenty year one years that they've been
drilled
thank you governor thank you mister
president the next question
goes to governor again from William hey
you did
governor reagan wage earners in this
country especially the young
are supporting a social security system
that continues to affect their income
drastically
the system is fostering a struggle
between the young and the old
in his dripping the country 20
polarization and these two groups
how much longer can the young
wage-earner expect to bear the
ever-increasing burden
the social security system
the social security system was based on
a false premise
with regard to how fast the number of
workers would increase in how fast the
number of retirees would increase
it is actuarially out a balance and this
first became
evident about sixteen years ago and some
others were voicing mornings then
now it is trillions have dollars how to
balance
and the only answer that has come so far
is the biggest single tax increase in
our nation's history
the payroll tax increase for social
security
which will only put a band-aid on this
and postpone the day of reckoning
by a few years at most what is needed
is a study that I a proposed by a task
force
to look to experts to look into this
entire problem as to how it can be
reformed and made actuarially sound but
with the premise that no one present be
depended on social security is going to
have the rug pulled out from under them
and not get their check we cannot
frightened as we have with the threats
in the campaign rhetoric that is going
on in this campaign
our senior citizens leave them thinking
that in some way they're endangered
and they would have no place to turn
they must continue to get those checks
and I believe that the system can be put
on a sound
actuarial basis it's going to take some
study and some work
and not just passing a tax increase to
let the load
or the roof fall in on the next
administration
that he would you repeat that question
for president carter
yes President Carter wage earners in
this country
specially on are supporting a social
security system
that continues to affect their income
drastically
the system is fostering a struggle
between young and old
in district in the country 20
polarization oh these two groups
how much longer Kenny young wage-earner
expect to bear the ever-increasing
burden
the social security system
as long as as a democratic president in
the white house we will have a strong
and viable
social security system free a threat a
bankruptcy
although governor reagan is changes
position lightly on four different
occasions he has advocated making social
security a voluntary system
which would in a back very quickly
bankrupted
I noticed also in the Wall Street
Journal earlier this week that a
preliminary report his passport
advocates
making social security's more sound
producing
the adjustments in social security for
the retired people
to compensate for the impact have
inflation
the scandal approach is a very dangerous
to the security
and the well-being and the peace of mind
other retired people in this country
and those approaching retirement age but
no matter what it takes in the future
to keep Social Security sound it must be
kept that way
and although there was a serious threat
to the social security system
and its integrity during the 1976
campaign about
and became president the action other
democratic congress working with me
has been to put social security back
home a sound
financial basis that's the way it will
stay
governor reagan well there just isn't
true
it is I said delayed the actuarial
I'm in balance a falling on us for just
a few years with an increase in taxes
and I don't believe we can go on
increasing the tax because the problem
for the young people today is that
they're paying in far more than I can
ever expected
to get out now again this statement that
somehow I wanted to destroy it and I
just changed
my tune and I'm was for voluntary social
security which would mean the ruin of it
mister president the voluntary thing
that I suggested many years ago
why's that a young man orphaned
and raised by an aunt who died
his aunt was ineligible for social
security insurance
because she was not his mother and I
suggested that this is an insurance
program
certainly the person who's paying in
should be able to name
his own beneficiaries and that's the
closest I've ever come
do anything voluntary with social
security
I to and pledged to a social security
program that will reassure the senior
citizens of ours
they're going to continue to get their
money there are some changes I'd like to
make
I would like to make a change that
discriminates in the regulations against
him
and wife who works and finds that she
then
is faced with the choice between heard
from other husbands benefits if he dies
first
or what she is paid in but it does not
recognize that she has also been
paying in herself and she is entitled to
more
she presently can get I'd like to change
that president carter's rebuttal now
I'm this constant
no suggestions that the basic social
security system should be
change does called concern and
consternation among the
aged about country it's obvious that we
should have a commitment to them
that social security benefit should not
be taxed know that would be no
peremptory change in the standard by
which
Social Security payments are made to the
retired people
we also need to continue to index the
social security payments
so that if inflation rises the social
security payments would rise
a commensurate degree the let the buying
power
other social security check continue
intact
in the past the relationship between
social security and medicare
has been very important to provide some
modicum
other aid for senior citizens and the
retention
up health benefits governor reagan as a
matter fact began his political career
campaigning around this nation
against medicare now we have an
opportunity to move toward national
health insurance
with an emphasis on the prevention of
disease
an emphasis on outpatient care not in
patient care
an emphasis on hospital cost containment
to hold down the cost of hospital care
for those who are ill an emphasis on
catastrophic health insurance
to live a family is threatened with
being wiped out economically because a
very well a very high
medical bill then the insurance would
help pay for it
these are the kind of element other
national health insurance important to
the american people
governor reagan again typically is
against
such a proposal governor
there you go again when I oppose
medicare
there was another piece of legislation
meeting the same problem before the
congress
I happen to favor the other piece of
legislation and thought that it would be
better for the senior citizens and
provide better care than the one
but was finally passed I was not
opposing the principal providing care
for them
I was opposing one piece of legislation
as
versus another there is something else
about social security course that
doesn't come out to the payroll tax it
comes out of the
general fund the something should be
done about
I think it's disgraceful that the
disability insurance fund in social
security
finds checks going every month to tens
of thousands of people who are locked up
in our institutions for crime
or from mental illness and they are
receiving disability checks
from social security every month pollen
state institution
provides for all their needs and their
care
president carter you have the last word
on this question
I think this debate on Social Security
medicare
national health insurance typifies as
vividly as any other
subject tonight the basic historical
differences between the Democratic Party
and the Republican Party the allusions
to basic changes in the minimum wage is
another
and the deleterious commented that the
governor reagan has made about
unemployment compensation
these commitments at the Democratic
Party has historically made to the
working families have this nation
have been extremely important to the
growth
in their stature and in a better quality
of life for them
I noticed recently that governor reagan
prequel a quote
Democratic president in his acceptance
address another what I have never heard
a candidate for president who is a
republican
quote a Republican president but when I
get an official
they try to govern like republicans so
it's good for the american people to
remember there's a sharp
basic historical different between
governor reagan me on these crucial
issues
also between the two parties that we
represent thank you mister president
governor reagan we now go to another
question
question to president carter by Barbara
Walters
from them you have addressed summer the
major issues tonight but the biggest
issue in the mind american voters is USA
homes
your ability to lead this country many
voters go into
that move just a week from today they
will be voting their got
instant about you man here already given
as your reasons why people should vote
for you now would you please tell us for
this your final question why they should
not vote for your opponent
why his presidency could be harmful to
the nation
and have been examine both your
opponent's record and the man himself
tell us his greatest weakness
by reluctant as I am sending critical
about governor reagan I'll try to answer
your question
first of all is a historical perspective
that i just described
this is a contest between a Democrat in
a mainstream love my party
as exemplified by the actions that have
taken an oval office last four years
as contrasted with governor reagan who
in most cases
does typify his pro day but in some
cases
there's a radical departure by him from
the Heritage
all eyes an hour and others
the most important crucial difference in
this election campaign in my judgment is
the approach to the control
up nuclear weaponry and the
inclination to control or not to control
the spread
atomic weapons to other nations I don't
present have a particular terrorist
nations
the incarnation the governor reagan his
example find
in May troubled times since he's been
running for president I think since 1968
to inject American military forces in
places like north korea
to put a blockade around cuba this year
all
in some instances to project american
forces into
a fishing dispute against all the small
nation a backward or
on the west coast of South America this
is typical of his long-standing
incarnation on the use of
American power-law not to resolve
disputes diplomatically and peacefully
but the show that they exercise at
military power
is best proven by the actual use of it
obviously no president want war
and I certainly do not believe the
governor again if he were president
would walk wall
but a president in the Oval Office has
to make a judgment
on almost a daily basis about how to
exercise enormous power country
for peace through diplomacy all
in a curious way in a belligerent at
attitude
which has example but his attitude
in the past blogger would you repeat the
question for governor again
from 10 realizing that you may be
equally reluctant to speak you love your
opponent mad
why people should not vote your opponent
why his presidency could be harmful to
the nation
and having examined both your opponent's
record and the man himself
could you tell us his greatest weekend
Barbara I believe that there is a
fundamental difference and I think it
has been evident in most to the answers
that
mister carter's given tonight that he
seeks the solution to anything
as another opportunity for a federal
government program
I happen to believe that the federal
government has usurped the powers and
don't wanna many
autonomy in authority to belongs back at
the state and local level
it has imposed on the individual freedom
to the people and that there are more of
these things that could be solved by the
people themselves
if they were given a chance or by the
levels of government that were closer to
them
now as to why I should be and he
shouldn't be
when he was a candidate 1976 President
Carter
invented I think he called the misery
index
he added the rate of unemployment and
the rated inflation
and it came at that time to 20.5
under president ford any said that no
man with that size mens rea index
had a right to seek reelection to the
presidency
today by his own decision
leave misery index is an excess
up 20 percent and I think this must
suggest
something but im
when I have quoted a democrat president
is the president says
I was a democrat I said many foolish
things back in those days
but the president that I quoted had made
a promise
a democrat prompts and I quoted him
because
it was never kept and today
you would find that that promise is at
the very heart
what republicanism represents in this
country today
and that's why I believe they're going
to be millions have democrats that are
going to vote with
past this time around because they too
want that promise kept
it was a promise for less government and
less taxes
and more freedom for the people
president carter
yes I mention the
radical departure of governor reagan
from their principles or ideals
a historical perspective on his own
party I don't like this can be better
illustrated than
in the case with guaranteeing women
people rights under the Constitution
about nation
for forty years the republican party
platforms
call poor guaranteeing women equal
rights
with a constitutional amendment 6
predecessors have man who served in the
oval office call for this guarantee a
women's rights
governor reagan and that new Republican
Party has departed from this commitment
a very severe blow to the opportunity
for women find it to correct
discrimination under which they have
suffered
when a man and a woman to the same
amount to work a man gets paid a dollar
a woman only get paid $15 and sent and
the equal rights amendment on Ascension
that equality albright's shall not be
abridged
for women by the federal government all
by the state government
that's all it surged a sub or guarantee
of equality of opportunity
which typifies the Democratic Party and
which is a very important commitment of
mine
as contrasted with governor reagan's
radical departure from
the long-standing policy of his own
party
governor reagan yes
its president once again I happen to be
against the amendment
because I think the amendment will take
this problem out of the hands of elected
legislators and put my hands when I like
the judges
I am for equal rights and while you have
been in office for four years and not
one single state
and most of them have a majority of
Democratic legislators
has added to the ratification or voted
to ratify the Equal Rights Amendment
while I was governor more than eight
years ago
I found fourteen separate instances
where women were discriminated against
in the body of california law
and I had passed and signed into law 14
statutes that eliminated
those discriminations including the
economic ones that you have just
mentioned equal pay and so forth
I believe that if we're all these years
that we've spent trying to get the
amendment
we spend as much time correcting these
laws as we did in california and we were
the first to do it
if I were president I would also now
take a look at the hundreds
I love federal regulations which
discriminate against women
and which mall right on well everyone is
looking for an amendment
I would have someone ride herd on those
regulations
and which start eliminating those
discriminations in the federal
government against women
president current how I'm a southern
and I share the basic beliefs have my
region about
an excessive government intrusion into
the private affairs American citizens
and also into the private affairs
the free enterprise system one other
commitment that I may wish to deregulate
the major industries
%uh this country we've been remarkably
successful with the help of the
democratic congress
we deregulate the air industry the rail
industry the trucking industry financial
institutions
now working on the communications
industry an additional and
I believe this element of discrimination
is something that I South has scene so
vividly
as a blight oh no region of the country
which has now been corrected
not only racial discrimination but
discrimination against people have to
work for a living
because we have been trying to pick
ourselves up but bootstraps
sent the long depression years
and lead appalled and useful life in the
affairs of this country we made
remarkable success
is part of my consciousness and my
commitment to continue this progress
so my heritage as a southerner my
experience in the Oval Office
convinces me that what I just described
as a proper course for the future
governor reagan yours is the last word
well my last word is again to save with
this
we were talking about this very simple
amendment in women's rights
I'm a good plan again I am for women's
rights but I would like to call
the tension people to the fact that a
step show called simple amendment
could be used by mister his men to
destroy discriminations that properly
belong by law to women
respecting the physical differences
between the two sexes
labor laws that protect them against
doing things that would be physically
harmful to them
those were all could all be challenged
my men
and the same would be true with regard
to combat service in the military and so
forth
I thought there was a subject we were
supposed to be on but if we're talking
about
how much we think about the working
people and so forth I'm the only further
than ever ran for this job
who was six times president of his own
Union and still is a lifetime membership
in that union
gentleman need to you now have three
minutes for
a closing statement president carter
your first
first to like to thank the label League
of Women Voters for making this
debate possible I think it's been a very
constructive debate
and I hope it helped to quite the
American people with a sharp differences
between myself and governor reagan
also want to thank the people Cleveland
and Ohio be in touch hospitable host
during this last few hours in my life
have been present now for
almost four years I had to make 1000
a decision and each one of those
decisions has been a learning process
i've seen the strength my nation and
i've seen the crises that it approached
inattentive way
and I've had to deal with those crises
as best I could
as I've said the record between myself
and governor reagan
I've been impressed with the stark
differences that exist between
I think the result of this debate
indicate but that fact is true
I consider myself in the mainstream of
my party I consider myself an amine
mainstream even up the bipartisan
list to president who served before me
the United States must be
a nation strong the United States must
be a nation
secure we must have a society this just
and play a and we must extend the
benefit of our own commitment to peace
to create a peaceful world
I believe that since I've been in office
they've been 608
areas of combat evolved in other parts
of the world
in each cage I alone have had to
determine the interest of my country
and the degree of involvement my country
I've done that but moderation with care
with thoughtfulness
sometimes consulting expert but I've
learned
in his last three and a half years that
went issue is extremely difficult
when the call is very close the chances
are the experts will be divided almost
50-50
in the final judgment about the future a
nation
war PC involvement reticence
thoughtfulness care consideration
concerned
has to be made by the man in the Oval
Office
let alone a job but with involving to
the american people in the process with
an open government
the job is a very gratifying one the
American people now facing
next tuesday a lonely decision
those listening to my boys will have to
make a judgment about the future this
country
and I think they'll remember that one
bow to make a lot of different
if one vote per precinct had changed in
1960 John Kennedy would never have been
president
this nation have a few more people had
gone to the polls and voted in 1968
hubert humphrey would have been
president richard nixon would not
there is a partnership involving in our
nation to stay strong
to stay at peace the Rays had a ban on
human rights
to set an example for the rest of the
world to let ID beliefs and commitments
be fell about others
in all the nations is my plan for the
future
I S American people to join me in this
partition
governor reagan because I would like to
have my words of thanks
to to the ladies have the the League of
Women Voters
making these debates possible I'm sorry
that
we couldn't persuade the
bringing into the third candidate so
that he could have been seen also in
these debates
but still it's good that at least once
all three of us were heard by the people
in this country
next tuesday is election day next
tuesday olive you will go to the polls
you stand there in the polling place
make a decision
I think when you make that decision it
might be well if you would ask yourself
are you better off than you were four
years ago
is it easier for you to go and buy
things in the stores and was four years
ago
is there more or less unemployment in
the country
and there was four years ago is america
has respected throughout the world as it
was
do you feel that our security is
as safe but we're a strong as we were
four years ago
and if you answer all those questions
yes why then I think your choice is very
obvious
do you vote for if you don't agree
if you don't think that this course that
we've been on for the last four years is
what you would like to see us follow
over the next four
then I could suggest another choice that
you have
this country doesn't have to be
in the shape that it is in we do not
have to go down go on
sharing and scarcity with the country
getting worse off
with unemployment growing we talk about
the unemployment lines
he followed the unemployed today we were
in a single line allowing two feet
breach 10 the midline would reach from
New York City to Los Angeles
californians
although this can be cured and all that
can be solved
I have not had the experience to the
president as head in holding that office
but I think in being governor of
California the most populous state in
the Union
if it were a nation that would be the
seventh ranking economic power in the
world
I too had some only moments and
decisions to make
I know that the economic program that I
have proposed for this nation
in the next few years can resolve many
other problems the trouble is today
I know because we did their
week %uh the cost the increased cost of
government
the increase in half over the eight
years we returned 5.7 billion dollars
in tax rebates credits and cuts to our
people
we as I said earlier fell below the
national average in
inflation when we did that and I know
that
we didn't give back authority and
autonomy to the people
I would like to have a crusade today and
I would like to lead the crusade with
your help
and it would be one to take government
off the backs of the great people of
this country
and turn you loose again to do those
things that I know
you can do so well because you did the
man made this country great
thank you gentleman ladies and gentleman
for sixty years the League of Women
Voters has been committed to citizen
education and the effective
participation
Americans in governmental in political
affairs
the most critical element at all in that
process is an informed citizen who goes
to the polls on Google Maps
on badly wound motors now I would like
to thank President Carter
and governor reagan